Thankyou.
Well, it has been a great pleasure to meet
you Sam, and Lin.
Yes, we've enjoyed meeting you too Victor.
Yes, it's been great. What a pity you have
to go home.
Well, all good things must come to an end.
But I'm sure we'll meet again.
Yes, I hope so.
And good luck with your business. I'm sure
it will go well.
And I wish you every success too.
Well, I think we should drink a toast to the
end of the conference, and to ourselves. Here's
to us.
Cheers
Cheers.
We should keep in touch.
Yes. Have I given you my card?
No - thanks very much.
Here's mine.
Do you have a card Lin?
Yes.
Thank you. I'll send you an email. And if
you're ever in Singapore, you must look me
up.
We certainly will. And you have my number.
When you're next in Sydney, give me a call
- we'll have a drink.
May I take these?
Well, I'd better get going or I'll miss my
flight.
Have a good flight home. Bon voyage.
Goodbye. Until next time.
Goodbye.
For the final program in the series we're
looking at some of the phrases you may use
when you're saying goodbye to someone - either
for a short time, or a long time. In our example,
Victor is from another country, and he's about
to go back home. At a conference, he's met
Sam and Lin.
It has been a great pleasure to meet you Sam
and Lin.
We've enjoyed meeting you too Victor.
Yes, it's been great. What a pity you have
to go home.
There are various phrases you can use to express
how enjoyable it was to meet someone. Which
one you use depends on how well you got to
know them. Practise some of these phrases
with Victor.
It's been a great pleasure to meet you.
I have enjoyed meeting you.
I'm so glad to have met you.
Nice to meet you.
The phrase 'nice to meet you' would be used
after one short meeting. You can also use
this phrase when you are introduced to someone.
What about the replies? Practise them with
Lin.
Nice to meet you.
You too.
It's been a pleasure to meet you.
And you.
Glad to have met you.
Glad to have met you too.
Notice that the reply should match the statement.
So if someone says: I have enjoyed meeting
you, the reply can be, So have I.
If someone says, "It's been a pleasure to
meet you," the reply can be, "A pleasure to
meet you too", or just "And you". Victor also
says, "I'm sure we'll meet again."
Here are some useful phrases to do with meeting
again. Practise them with Victor.
I'm sure we'll meet again.
Hopefully we'll meet again.
I hope we'll meet again soon.
Notice again here that the reply should match
the statement, so if someone says, "I'm sure
we'll meet again," then the reply also uses
'am': So am I. After the statement, "I hope
we'll meet again", the reply should be, "So
do I".
Another part of saying goodbye can be wishing
someone well for the future.
And good luck with your business. I'm sure
it will go well.
And I wish you every success too.
Sam proposes a toast. Watch how he does this.
Well, I think we should drink a toast to the
end of the conference, and to ourselves. Here's
to us. Cheers.
Cheers.
This is an informal toast. Sam says, "I think
we should drink a toast".
Another phrase he could use is 'Let's drink
to'. For example, 'Let's drink to the end
of the conference' or 'Let's drink to our
future meeting'. Then they clink their glasses
together and say 'Cheers'.
Here's another version of the toast:
Let's drink to our next meeting.
Our next meeting!
Cheers
And of course, the toast doesn't have to be
alcohol, it can be any kind of drink.
The next part of their conversation is about
keeping in touch, or keeping in contact.
We should keep in touch.
Yes. Have I given you my card?
No - thanks very much. Here's mine.
Do you have a card Lin?
Yes.
Thank you. I'll send you an email.
Repeat the phrases after Sam.
We must keep in touch.
We must keep in contact.
Here's my card.
Would you like my card?
Do you have a card?
The next part of their conversation is about
meeting again. Listen:
And if you're ever in Singapore, you must
look me up.
We certainly will. And you have my number.
When you're next in Sydney, give me a call
- we'll have a drink.
To 'look someone up' just means to arrange
a meeting. When Victor says, "You must look
me up", he is inviting Sam and Lin to meet
him if they are in Singapore. This is more
of a social invitation, than a business one.
Using the word 'must' is not like an order
here - it suggests that Victor will be very
happy if Sam sees him in Singapore.
In the same way, Sam says, "Give me a call"
to Victor. It sounds like an order, but in
fact it's an invitation. It's important to
get the intonation - the way you say it - right,
so that it sounds like an invitation, and
not an order.
You must look me up when you're in Singapore.
And if I don't?
I'll never speak to you again!
Practise these kinds of invitations with Victor.
You must look me up next time you're in town.
You must come and see me.
Why don't you give me a call when you're in
town?
Ring me if you're in town.
Finally let's look at how the three friends
say goodbye. Remember this is a semi-formal
situation.
Well, I'd better get going or I'll miss my
flight.
Have a good flight home. Bon voyage.
Goodbye. Until next time.
Goodbye.
There are a few ways of saying goodbye but
the simplest and best is simply 'good bye'.
Sam says "bon voyage" - a French phrase which
is also quite common for someone who is travelling.
Now, let's review and practise some of the
phrases we've learnt today.
It's been a pleasure to meet you.
I'm sure we'll meet again.
We must keep in touch.
Give me a call when you're in town.
I've enjoyed meeting you.
I wish you every success for the future.
May I give you my card?
Best wishes for the future.
I hope you have a good flight home.
The language you use in each situation may
be slightly different depending on how well
you know the other people, and how friendly
you are with them. If the situation is social,
and you have become quite friendly, you may
use slightly less formal language. But it's
important not to forget the usual expressions
of good wishes - such as for a good flight
home, and to say how you've enjoyed meeting
the other person. But don't go too far.
Well, I'd better get going or I'll miss my
flight.
I'm going to miss you Victor.
So am I. What will we do without you?
Be strong.
Will we meet again?
I know we will.
Goodbye.
Goodbye Victor - and bon voyage.
You forgot my card!
Well, I've enjoyed helping you with The Business
of English, and I hope you've enjoyed learning
some useful phrases and expressions in English
- and that you'll be able to put them into
practice soon.
Goodbye and good luck!